Hi, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף Daf is סמך. Samech. We
begin at the bottom of נ"ט עמוד ב' Nun Tet Amud Bet
and we are one, two, three, four, five lines down in the
wide lines. Last word on the line, ולא בקטלא. Velo be-Katla. These
are various things that a woman could have worn on שבת Shabbat
outdoors because of a concern that it'll come to be taken off
and carried, at least that's the way the גמרא Gemara explains it.
Interestingly, the משנה Mishnah never tells you what the problem is. Anyway,
ולא בקטלא. Velo be-Katla.
So what's my קטלא? Katla? says the גמרא. Gemara. Six lines down
in the wide lines: מנכתא דפארי, Minkata de-Parei, something that basically is
a type of a small bib,
and apparently though not made just to catch food but some type
of like of a breastplate or something that suspends from the neck
and again, assumingly presumably there's a concern that it'll come to be
removed. נזמים, Nezamim, how about rings? So נזמי האף, Nizmei ha-Af, nose
rings, not earrings. Why not?
רש"י ותוספות Rashi and Tosafot both say that earrings would be too
complicated to remove and we're not concerned they'll be removed. Now never
having seen anybody wear nose rings, it would still appear to be
that nose rings are probably more of a effort to remove than
earrings, but what do I know? Anyway, interestingly it says that it's
dealing with nose rings and not earrings. ולא בטבעת שאין עליה חותם
Velo be-Taba'at she'ein Aleha Chotam and not a finger ring that does
not have a non-signet ring and because as we'll see, because it's
a non-signet ring, so again the concern is that you'll come to
remove it. It's a דרבנן De-Rabbanan concern. So if you do it,
it's only דרבנן De-Rabbanan transgression. If it has a signet ring, then
it's a biblical concern, then even though you're wearing it, it's not
fundamentally jewelry, it's fundamentally your way of taking around your seal, but
it's a convenient way of carrying it on your ring, at least
that's the way the גמרא Gemara understands. So let's take a look.
The גמרא Gemara spells that out. היש עליה חותם, Ha-Yesh Aleha Chotam,
if it has on it a חותם, Chotam, so חייבת, Chayyevet, a
seal, you're חייבת Chayyevet because then it's carrying. It's considered a—not considered
a תכשיט. Takhshit. אלמא לאו תכשיטו, Alma Lav Takhshitu, so you see
that it's not—now you said necessarily you can't necessarily infer that straight
away from the line in the משנה, Mishnah, but it's explicit in
a next משנה, Mishnah, in like a further משנה Mishnah that when
it has a חותם Chotam it is actually considered biblically carrying. ורמינהו,
Ve-Raminhu, I'll ask you on this: תכשיטי נשים, Takhshitei Nashim, again a
משנה כלים Mishnah Kelim that says women's ornaments, women's
jewelry, טמאים Temei'in because they're considered like a type of a כלי
Kli even if it's something worn for jewelry. And here are a
list of some of women's jewelries: קטלאות, Katla'ot, these types of like
breastplates, you know or things suspended from the neck;
נזמים, Nezamim, rings, which here means earrings, because we'll see nose rings
will be mentioned in a minute; וטבעות Vetaba'ot and finger rings; וטבעת,
Ve-Taba'at, and when we're while we're talking regarding finger rings, בין שיש
עליה חותם בין שאין עליה חותם, Bein she-Yesh Aleha Chotam Bein she-Ein
Aleha Chotam, whether it has a חותם Chotam or not a חותם,
Chotam, either way it's jewelry and it could become טמא; Tamei; ונזמי
האף Ve-Nizmei ha-Af and nose rings. So we have two contradictions, or
at least two inconsistencies. One is which the גמרא Gemara doesn't pay
attention to, which is the earrings. So there רש"י ותוספות Rashi and
Tosafot both say yeah, earrings are jewelry and we're allowing you to
wear them because it's a type of jewelry we're not afraid you'll
take off. It's not in our list in the משנה, Mishnah, our
list was only jewelry we're afraid you would take off, for whatever
reason we're not afraid you'll take off earrings. But the bigger problem
is that this list says that a type of a jewelry is
rings that are signet rings. And a later משנה Mishnah is going
to tell us that a signet ring at least for a woman
where it was not considered the norm for women to wear signet
rings, we'll see it'll be different for men, but for a woman
to wear a signet ring would be considered to be jewelry—whereas—I'm sorry
that's what the משנה כלים Mishnah Kelim says, whereas our משנה Mishnah
says that later we'll see that if a woman wears a signet
ring it's carrying on שבת. Shabbat. So is it woman's jewelry or
not? If it's woman's jewelry then it's considered a vessel and could
become טמא. Tamei. Why if a woman wears a signet ring is
it considered carrying, biblical carrying on שבת? Shabbat? So the גמרא Gemara
says, ואמר רבי זירא—so Ve-Amar Rabbi Zeira רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira has
an answer, it's interesting that it introduces it with ואמר רבי זירא,
Ve-Amar Rabbi Zeira, not אמר רבי זירא. Amar Rabbi Zeira. Anyway, רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira answers, לא קשיא. Lo Kashya. No, here's the way
to reconcile this problem. Is a woman's signet ring considered jewelry or
not? הא רבי נחמיה הא רבנן, Ha Rabbi Nechemiah Ha Rabbanan, it's
based on a debate of רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemiah and the רבנן,
Rabbanan, there's a debate about this. דתניא, De-Tanya, we taught in a
ברייתא, Baraita,
היא של מתכת, Hi she-Metakhet, we quoted this before, if you have
a ring, this is again by question about טומאה וטהרה, Tum'ah ve-Taharah,
that is made out of metal, וחותמה של אלמוג, Vechotama shel Almog,
and the signet part, the seal part is made out of cedar,
then now the basic point is like this: is that this ring,
a normal finger ring does not have a בית קיבול, Beit Kibbul,
does not have a receptacle. So can a vessel without a receptacle
become טמא? Tamei? If it's a metal vessel, yes. Metal vessels as
long as it's defined as a כלי Kli can become טמא Tamei
even without a receptacle. A wood one has to have a בית
קיבול. Beit Kibbul. So let's say this vessel here, this ring is
part wood and part metal. The ring part is metal, the seal
part is wood or vice versa. So is it going to be
טמא Tamei or not? It depends what do you... considered to be
the central part of the vessel: the ring part or the seal
part. So the first assumption is that it's the ring part. היא
שמתכת וחותמה של אלמוג, Hi shematechet vechotama shel almog, if the ring
is of metal and the seal is cedar, טמאה, tmeiah, then it
can become טמא tamei because it is fundamentally a metal vessel, so
even though it does not have a receptacle. היא של אלמוג וחותמה
של מתכת, Hi shel almog vechotama shel matetchet, if it's made out
of cedar but the seal is made out of metal, then fundamentally
it's a wood vessel and טהורה tehorah cannot become... it is טהור
tahor cannot become טמא tamei because there's no receptacle. That's the first
opinion which says you basically define it by the ring part. רבי
נחמיה מטמא, Rabbi Nechemiah metamei, Rabbi Nechemiah says in the second case
where the seal is metal, it is טמא. tamei. שהיה רבי נחמיה
אומר, Shehayah Rabbi Nechemiah omer, Rabbi Nechemiah says בטבעת betabaat הולך אחר
חותמה. holech achar chotamah. When it comes to a signet ring, you
go by the signet. The signet defines the central part of the
ring in terms of what type of a vessel is it, wood
or metal. By the way, תוספות Tosafot says the reverse would also
be true. If the ring was metal and the seal was wood,
he would say it's טהור. tahor. He would say you always go
(thank you) by the seal part. That is what defines if they're
made out of different materials, that is what defines the nature of
the ring. So that's when it comes to signet ring. בעול, Beol,
if you have a yoke for a cow, for an ox, הולך
אחר סמלונה, holech achar simlonah, you go after the sort of the
vertical rods. Now רש"י Rashi explains that what they would have is
they did not have a yoke that was sort of a horseshoe
shape, as we found out yesterday they didn't have horseshoes either, of
our type of horses. Anyway, they did not have a like a
U-shaped yoke. What they had was a vertical yoke. I actually have
seen this in some pictures. You've got a vertical yoke going across
the neck of the cow... horizontal... and two vertical posts tightly next
to the neck so he can't move it. They say that's what
they do in China?
I think I've seen that. Okay, so you understand the
ideal: this is the yoke and you've got a vertical bar here
and a vertical bar here, then it stays on the neck of
the cow and it can't move. So he says let's say the
yoke is of wood and those vertical bars are of metal or
vice versa. Is it a metal vessel or a wood vessel? So
he says you go by those vertical bars that keep it in
place. Okay, which is interesting because you would think that the primary
part of it is the stuff on the top. By a ring
you could imagine that
the primary thing is the seal, but here it's a little interesting
that he says you go by that. בקולב, Bekolav,
now a קולב kolav
is a type of a frame that you would hang wares from.
So like a shopkeeper would hang wares from. So הולך אחר מסמרותיו,
holech achar masmerotav, you go by the nails, the things that the
things are hung from, which you sort of understand that because the
purpose is to hang things and the frame is only a way
of keeping those nails there so the nails are available to hang
things from them. So if it's got metal nails, it is טמא
tamei even if it's a wooden frame or can become טמא. tamei.
בסולם, Besulam, by a ladder, הולך אחר שליבותיו, holech achar shlibotav, you
go by the rungs of the ladder. You could also understand that
the primary thing you're using is the rungs. So the only thing
that to me doesn't sort of fit this pattern is the bars
of the yoke. But anyway, בערסי, Bearsi, with an ערסי arsi where
רש"י Rashi says ערסא, arsa, which is a type of a scales,
הולך אחר שלשלותיו. holech achar shalshilotav. So they have a very nice
picture of that in the Steinsaltz. But you're basically hold a like
is it Lady Liberty? No, she's holding like Lady Justice, but she
holds like a bar type of thing. This would be something you
would like suspend by, it would have like a chain and then
it would have a bar and one side would be the, right,
scales of justice. Yeah. Is that what she, or is she holding
something that's more like a bar, Lady Justice, or is she holding
something that looks like...
Typically it's just depicted as picking two balances...
two balances. Yeah, the Steinsaltz has a balance and a weight and
a weight. But anyway, so the point is you've got let's say
the bar is made out of wood and the receptacle is made
out of wood, but let's say the chains are made out of
metal. So he says you go by the chains. Now again there
it's a little harder to understand because the chains are not as
central to how you're using it, it sort of all operates together.
So anyway, but that's what he says. You look at those components.
Maybe those components tend to be metal and he's more inclined to
consider it טמא, tamei, so he looks at those components. וחכמים אומרים,
Vachachamim omrim, and the sages say הכל הולך אחר המעמיד. hakol holech
achar hamaamid.
You go by what gives it sort of form and shape. Now
you can't always identify that. Maybe the better the case where that's
more obvious would be like the frame and the ladder where there
presumably be the sidebars of the ladder, not the rungs, or the
basic frame which would be what gives it sort of stance and
gives it shape. By some of these others to me it's not
so clear what you identify as the מעמיד. maamid. But here becomes
a debate about something made of various components: do you define it
as metal or wood, which part you look at. Now how is
that relevant for us? It's relevant for us because the rabbis go
by the ring part of a signet ring and... And רבי נחמיה
Rabbi Nechemia *Rabbi Nechemiah* goes by the signet part. So what's being
said is, is this, is a signet ring considered jewelry or not?
So interestingly, the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* assuming the same that when we say,
when there's a משנה Mishna *mishna* that says that it's considered jewelry,
that's the Rabbis who always look at the who always look at
the ring part. So even if it's got a signet component, that
is not the focus, the focus is that it's a ring. So
therefore they consider it jewelry and therefore they wouldn't have a problem
with wearing a signet ring on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*, at least not
a biblical problem, rabbinic maybe, because of you'll come take it off,
but biblically it would be considered jewelry. The our משנה Mishna *mishna*
that says that a woman wearing a signet ring is a biblical
problem, it's not jewelry, that's רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia *Rabbi Nechemiah*, who
says with a signet ring the signet is what's key. So it's
really not something that's there for you to wear, it's really not
a jewelry, it's really a way of carrying around a signet, a
way of carrying around a seal. So therefore it's carrying and it's
not jewelry and that is רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia *Rabbi Nechemiah*. Yes,
you had a question Charlie? No?
No. Okay. Yes? Would carrying would be even with an עירוב eruv
*eruv* because it would be מוקצה *muktsa* the signet ring?
Would be no, not מוקצה *muktsa*. It would be because it's like
the example I told you before like, you know, רב משה *Rav
Moshe* was asked about like wearing a wristwatch. How much do you
say is a wristwatch just a convenient way of carrying around a
mini clock, so it's convenient to carry around my wrist, but fundamentally
it's not jewelry and it's not clothing, or would you say fundamentally
it is jewelry and clothing, it also happens to tell the time.
So what the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* saying is that if you look at
a signet ring and you say the key here is the signet,
the seal part, right, so then even though you're wearing it on
your finger, you're not it's not clothing and it's not jewelry, it's
a way of carrying around a seal, so it's like holding it
in your hand, so it's carrying.
But what I'm asking, isn't it מוקצה *muktsa* because you wouldn't use
it on שבת Shabbos *Shabbos*?
That might be true, but we're considered more about the concerned about
the biblical aspect of it as carrying, right.
See, but who would wear who
would wear a signet ring
without needing to use it? Why not?
I'm sure like I'm sure it also served as jewelry a function
of jewelry. Right. You know, it's got a ring. What? I don't
know, this one looks nicer, who knows? Okay, but that's the exact
question. Are we going to say that even if you're wearing it
for ornament and for jewelry purposes, objectively right we're going to define
it as a type of as a jewelry. Look, this is very
relevant for as רבקה Rivka *Rivka* says when you don't have an
עירוב eruv? *eruv* and then they do all these interesting things with
keys like a key pin and this and that, you know, how
much you know can you really call it jewelry or is it
really just a convenient way of carrying around your key?
No one would really
be wearing it unless—no, I totally disagree. שבת Shabbos, *Shabbas* keys, yes.
שבת Shabbos, *Shabbas* keys, signet rings you could imagine being worn for
jewelry. Okay, so that's answer number one. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
continues. Says like this: רבא אמר לצדדין קתני *Rava amar letzdadin kitani*.
רבא *Rava* says the משנה Mishna *mishna* that says that it's
jewelry and can become טמא tamei, *tamei* does not and should not
be read as saying that all those rings are women's jewelry. יש
עליו חותם תכשיט איש *Yesh alecha chotam tachshit ish*, a ring whether
it has a seal or not is jewelry, but not always women's
jewelry. אם עליו חותם *Im alecha chotam* with a seal on it
then it would be a man considered a man's jewelry, that would
be considered more accepted more norm for a man to wear. אין
עליו חותם *Ein alecha chotam* without a seal then תכשיט אשה *tachshit
isha* it would be woman's jewelry. I mean you sort of see
this, you know, men sometimes wear these like, you know, class rings
or you know like these huge thick rings or whatever you can
never imagine a woman wearing a ring like that, right? I mean
to me it always looks ugly on a man also, but okay.
Anyway, so the גמרא'ס *Gemara's* saying is that based on whatever the
norms were now you know might also be norms of assuming that
men would be more involved or maybe the reality was that they
were much more involved in business dealing than had reasons to have
signet rings than women, so the norms were was that it was
considered as a jewelry for a man and not for a woman.
So our and that's consistent with what our משנה'ס *mishna's* going to
say by שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. A later משנה'ס *mishna's* going to say
that if a woman wears a signet ring, again most of these
issues until now have been rabbinic, but if a woman wears a
signet ring it's considered a burden, not jewelry and carrying biblically. And
if a man wears a signet ring, no, it is jewelry. So
it's not biblical carrying. So the our משנה Mishna. *mishna* later going
to say exactly that difference, it was not the norm for a
woman to wear and therefore considered a burden. Again, it's a little
interesting. Okay, but at the end of the day, but let's say
she really is wearing it for jewelry purposes. And it seems that
at some stage we said we saw an extreme example yesterday about
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* and this tiara, this עיר של זהב *ir
shel zahav*, that at some stage if the Rabbis say this is
completely not the norm within society then even if it's being worn
for jewelry purposes it's considered to be a burden. So that's the
reality that what we're going to say later about a woman and
a signet ring, and here we're saying when the משנה *mishna* says
they're both considered jewelry and can become טמא tamei. *tamei*, yes, but
a signet ring only if it's man's jewelry, not if not for
women. Okay, that's answer number two. Answer number three says, רב נחמן
בר יצחק אמר *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar*, טומאה Tuma? ושבת קרמית
*Tuma veshabbat karamit*? Now this is a very lovely answer even before
we see what he's going to spell out because it's always very
important when the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* compares different
halakhic categories.
You know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* often works with an assumption that
we can just apply one definition from one area to another. So
if something is defined
as... and think about it in any area of secular law, where
would you ever think that? Like, if you have some, you know,
some law about, I don't know,
about some, you know,
governing a port, and it had a definition of a ship, you
wouldn't necessarily think that the same definition should apply in some completely
different area of, like, civil law or something. Right? Why should we
take from one definition to another? Each one has its own concerns.
But the גמרא Gemara often assumes, no, if it's a vessel here,
it's a vessel there, and so on. So the very, just these
three words before we even see how they get unpacked, are very
important. What are you doing, comparing שבת Shabbos. to טומאה? Tuma טומאה
Tuma, has one definition, שבת Shabbat. has another definition. Okay, and now
we're going to see why. Okay, so טומאה, Tuma, כלי מעשה אמר
רחמנא, kli ma'aseh amar Rachmana, וכליהו. v'kilyahu. By טומאה, Tuma. there's no
הלכה halakha that it has to be considered clothing or jewelry. Anything
that's a vessel can become טמא, tamei. right? So you can, you
know, you can have a toothpick, you can have a fork, you
can have, you know, any of the million types of possible vessels
in the world. That's by טומאה. Tuma Anything that's a vessel can
become טמא. tamei שבת, Shabbat משום משא אמר רחמנא. mishum masa amar
Rachmana. By שבת, Shabbat we're talking only about a very small category,
only something that is clothing or jewelry. Anything else is a burden.
I don't care that it's a vessel, it's a burden. So אין
עליה חותם תכשיט, ein aleha chosam tachshit, without a seal it is
jewelry and it's acceptable to wear, at least biblically. יש עליה חותם,
yesh aleha chosam, if it's got a seal, משא, masa, then it's
not jewelry. Then it's fundamentally, there's a seal, so therefore it's a
problem. Meaning when the משנה said by כלים, keilim, jewelry includes rings,
and then parentheses it says whether it has a seal or it
doesn't have a seal, what it meant is whether it has a
seal or it doesn't have a seal, it can become טמא. tamei,
But not because both of those are considered jewelry. Without a seal,
it's jewelry. With a seal, it's a vessel, not jewelry. It's a
vessel, so it could become טמא tamei, because it's something you use
to, you know, to seal—you know how they used signet rings, right?
I haven't said it because I assume everybody knows. You take it
to the wet wax and you seal your thing on it. So
it's a type of a vessel. So fine. So when the משנה
said it could become טמא, tamei, it was not because it was
considered jewelry. It was because with a seal, it's not jewelry, but
it's a vessel. That's for טומאה Tuma, הלכה. halakha. For שבת הלכה,
Shabbos halacha, as soon as it stops being jewelry, it automatically is
considered a burden and therefore cannot be, you know, biblically would be
a problem wearing it on שבת. Shabbat So you put all these
answers together basically, they all agree. I mean they can't disagree because
our משניות Mishnayos are going to say it later, that for a
woman to wear a signet ring was considered not jewelry and biblical
carrying, and for a man it would be considered jewelry, it would
be within the norms and would not be carrying. And for טומאה,
Tuma, either when it says that it's a problem either there's either—well
for טומאה, tumah. either it's talking about a man's signet ring, which
is why it calls it jewelry, or it's talking about a woman's
but it's not jewelry, it's just a vessel. And then one final
answer which was רבי נחמיה that actually said that you distinguish between
רבי נחמיה and the רבנן. Rabbanan. But the basic two final answers
were to distinguish between whether the ring is the עיקר ikar or
the signet part is the עיקר. ikar. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara continues: ולא במחט שאינה נקובה. V'lo b'machat she'eina nekuva.
So one thing is she can wear is a ring without a
seal, that's only a rabbinic problem. With a seal, it'll be a
biblical problem. Now we go on with the needle. And she cannot
wear a needle without a hole. Same type of idea. If it
has a hole, then it's considered carrying, it's not even jewelry. But
without a hole, it's considered a piece of the clothing, it's not
biblical carrying, but she can't wear it where for—maybe she'll take it
off. So למאי חזיא? L'mai chazya? What would a woman normally use
this for? So אמר רב יוסף: Amar Rav Yosef: הואיל ואשה אוגרת
בה שערה. Ho'il v'isha ogeret bah se'arah. So רש"י Rashi says what
it means is that she has some of her hair coming out
of her cap and she uses it like, you know, like it's
one of those like long knitting needles almost type of thing and
you would like wrap the hair around it. Like they do in,
like in Japan, right? They do that sometimes, right? But a long,
like, pin that they would wrap it around, the hair that came
out of the hat. תוספות Tosafos says, and I'll go by תוספות
Tosafos because it fits a little better with the continuing גמרא, Gemara
that actually it would be a pin that she would use to
keep her hairnet on tightly so it would not slip off. Okay.
So therefore it is functioning, a hatpin, but something that
is important for a lot of guys who use hairpins for their
כיפות. kippos.
Oh, okay, there you go, like right, like exactly. So therefore it
is considered a type of a clothing because it functions with the
piece, with the clothing to keep the clothing on. Okay, so therefore
it's not a biblical problem, it's only a rabbinic problem. אמר ליה
אביי: Amar lei Abaye: What?
What's the rabbinic problem?
Again, we're afraid she'll take it off, but now we're going to
see why should we be afraid? אמר ליה אביי: Amar lei Abaye:
ותהוי כבירית טהורה ותשתרי. V'tehavi k'virit tehora v'tishari. Let it be like
the בירית, birit, which is טהורה tehora and let it be allowed.
Now what's the בירית? birit? בירית Birit is a type of also
a clasp that was used to keep on some leggings. Okay, and
that's exactly the way תוספות Tosafos understands אביי. Abaye. The clasp is
not considered, it cannot be טמא, tamei, why? Because it is not
an ornament. If it was an ornament, it would be טמא, tamei.
but it's there to be a vessel to serve to keep the
clothing in place. So if you remember, a vessel for an animal
or a vessel for a vessel is not able to become טמא,
tamei. only a vessel directly used by a person. So this is
a clasp used to keep up the leggings, it's טהור. tahor. But
according to that, the emphasis is the fact that it's טהור tahor
shows we don't consider it an ornament. And therefore, you're allowed to
go out with this legging clasp on שבת. Shabbat, We're not afraid
you'll take it off. We're only afraid you'll show your friend your
nice ornament, your nice jewelry. We're not afraid you'll show them some
type of a clasp that's there just to hold up the clothing.
So therefore, if this is the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, if
this is a hairpin to keep the hat from flying off, we
shouldn't be afraid you'll take it off. It's not jewelry, you're not
going to show it to your friend, just like this thing there
for the legging. רש"י Rashi says that it's not about the fact
that
it's
only there to keep the thing in place, but רש"י Rashi says
that by both of those there's a צניעות tzniut issue. You wouldn't
start undoing your clasp on your legging to show somebody because that
wouldn't be צניעות, tzniut, and you're not going to undo your hairpin
because it's also revealing your hair and it's a צניעות tzniut issue.
Okay, but either way the גמרא Gemara, says if that's what it
is, there should not have been a rabbinic problem. אלא תרגמה רב
אדא נרשאה קמיה דרב יוסף, Ela tirgema Rav Adda Narshaa kammai deRav
Yosef, so רב אדא Rav Adda from נרשאה Narshaa explains in front
of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, חובנת אשה חולקת בה שערה. hovnet isha
holeket bah se'arah. So it says, well, during the week this is
used as a way of like of splitting her hair, I don't
even understand, some type of a comb, some type of way she'd
like you know make a part in her hair. So the גמרא
Gemara. says ותנא בשבת למאי חזיא, v'tana b'Shabbat l'mai hazya, very nice,
but for שבת Shabbat what would she be wearing it for? Meaning
or you know, so meaning
so how could we think or the way תוספות Tosafot explains this
is how could we think by שבת Shabbos. it's not a biblical
problem? Why is it only a rabbinic issue? I mean, if you're
basically like a comb you're carrying out with you, so it's carrying.
What makes it okay rabbinically? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבא
טס של זהב יש על ראשה. Amar Rava tas shel zahav yesh
al rosha. So basically, this is a type of a pin or
of of of a needle that has some type of a gold
plate at one end. ובחול חולקת בו שערה. uv'chol holeket bo se'arah.
So in the weekday she carries it out and maybe puts it
in her pocket and she's using it to as some way of
of making a part in her hair. I really don't understand the
mechanics. ובשבת מניחתה כנגד פדחתה. uv'Shabbat menihata k'neged padahta. On שבת Shabbos,
she'll put it like just she'll attach it to her hat and
she'll have a type of a you know something on her forehead
and basically it's a type of a jewelry. So what he winds
up explaining it is, by the way, I think the easiest way
to understand this is you actually have sometimes these combs, right these
are very right right
porcelain or you know whatever
ivory combs that you put in the hair and they can function
as jewelry, you can also use as a comb, right? Take it
out and use as a comb. So it's something of that nature
and therefore what he's saying is that the old problem that you
would come to show it to your friend, you'll come to take
it out and it's somewhat ornamental and you'll come to show it
to your friend.
And then part of your hair that's would be immodest to reveal.
Well, רש"י Rashi says that,
yeah, well no, because you're just pulling the comb out, it's not
keeping your hair wrapped up, it's just sort of stuck in there.
Yeah. All right, so those again are the list of things that
are that are considered to be ornaments or jewelry, not a biblical
problem but they are rabbinic one, we're afraid you'll take it out.
And again the last thing we saw was the interesting distinction by
the ring, that you have a possibility according to רבי נחמיה that
or the one way of reading it is that the emphasis on
the signet is only רבי נחמיה'ס Rabbi Nechemia's position, the חכמים Chachamim
would say even a signet ring is considered jewelry. But the basic
conclusion of the גמרא Gemara seemed to be that a signet ring
like we'll see in our later משנה for a woman was not
considered jewelry. It's that it does go by norms presumably regardless of
why it might have been worn, that a signet ring would be
a issue for a woman, but that does not mean that it
is not a vessel for טומאה. Tumah And again I just repeat
that because that's important to acknowledge that the definitions of jewelry for
שבת, Shabbos you know you don't just assume and the categories are
the same. טומאה has one list of concerns, it's this goes by
big category of vessels, שבת Shabbos is a much more narrow category
of clothing and jewelry.
So you're saying a regular ring for woman is or is not
a rabbinic problem?
It's a rabbinic problem. But with a seal it's even a biblical
problem.
Exactly, so at least so these days I mean all
right so with an עירוב eruv, it's different. But even without an
עירוב? eruv?
Well, without an עירוב, so did we say that women can't wear...?
So all right, so that's an interesting thing as we look and
as we asked at the beginning of the פרק, perek, if the
if we haven't said it yet in the גמרא, Gemara. but if
we're going to say that some of this stuff you can't even
go out into the courtyard with because we'll say that if we
let you out in the courtyard you'll go out into the רשות
הרבים, reshut harabbim, would that apply today with an עירוב? Maybe not,
because now there's like not an immediate רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim. But
anyway, we'll talk about maybe we'll find some time near the end
to talk about הלכה. halakha, But let's just continue to look at
at these cases of various pieces of clothing. So the next
משנה. לא יצא האיש בסנדל המסומר. Lo yetze ha'ish b'sandal hamusummar. to
the base. And a sandal with nails you cannot go out with
on שבת. Shabbos. Or ever, right? Well, no, just on שבת, Shabbos
we'll see. ולא ביחיד, V'lo beyachid, you cannot wear an individual, a
single shoe, בזמן שאין ברגלו מכה, bizman she'ein beraglo maka,
unless there is a wound on your leg. And then the question
will be, which therefore, if there is a wound on your leg,
which foot can have the individual shoe, the one with the leg
or without the leg? Now what's the problem of going out with
a single shoe? So רש"י Rashi says the
problem is, he has two opinions. One is people will think, if
you're wearing one shoe on your foot, like waiting for the other
shoe to drop, people will think that the other shoe maybe you're
carrying, and people will suspect you of carrying. רש"י Rashi doesn't like
that, that we're introducing this whole thing of suspicion here. רש"י Rashi
says the problem is, is that for whatever reason you're wearing one
shoe, you lost your other, whatever, but people are going to make
fun of you, you're walking around with one shoe, so you might
get embarrassed and take off one of the, take the shoe off
and come to carry that shoe. So don't go around wearing just
one shoe. Anyway, we'll talk about that in גמרא. Gemara. ולא בתפילין,
V'lo bitfillin, you can't wear תפילין tefillin on שבת Shabbos outdoors, it's
a type of non-clothing. It would be considered again, whether it's biblical
or rabbinic, we're going to see in a minute, all this is
rabbinic.
ולא בקמיע, V'lo bekamia, do not wear an amulet, בזמן שאינו מן
המומחה, bizman she'eino min hamumcheh, if it's not from an expert, but
if it is from an expert you're allowed to wear it. ולא
בשריון ולא בקסדה ולא במגפיים, V'lo beshiryon v'lo bekasda v'lo bemagafayim,
you cannot wear armor or a helmet or leg armor. ואם יצא,
V'im yatza, and if you did any of this, אינו חייב חטאת,
eino chayav chatas, none of this is biblical carrying, again these are
all rabbinic problems. So it will be interesting to see that this
issue about the תפילין tefillin and the קמיע kamia and all these
are only rabbinic problems, none of this is considered to be biblical
carrying.
Right, why is an amulet permitted altogether?
Well, we will discuss that. That is we have a שבת Shabbos
anyway? What? Yes, so we will discuss all of that, okay? So
that's all though tomorrow's דף, daf, so come back tomorrow, it's a
cliffhanger. All the stuff here that caught your attention is tomorrow's דף.
daf. Today's דף daf is all going to be about the sandal
with nails. Let's take a look. Okay. סנדל המסומר מאי טעמא, Sandal
hamesumar mai ta'ama, what's the problem with the nailed sandal? So אמר
שמואל, Amar Shmuel, שלפי הגזירה היו. shulfei hagezeira hayu.
שלוף shuluf means like to pull out. So people that would try
to avoid the, you know, the edict, meaning when there would be
a persecution and they would be, you know, and they would be
prohibited to be doing מצוות. mitzvos. So people, there would be a
group of people that obviously would go into hiding and try to
keep up doing, continue the מצוות. mitzvos. So let's see what the
story was. והיו נחבאים במערה, V'hayu nechba'im beme'ara, they would hide in
a cave. ואמרו, V'amru,
and they said, הנכנס יכנס והיוצא אל יצא. hanichnas yikanes v'hayotzei al
yeitzei. Anybody can come into the cave but nobody's allowed to leave
because they're afraid that if somebody will leave that, you know, you
can see as רש"י Rashi says, when you're about to go in
you can look around and see if anybody's following you and then
go into the secret entrance. But when you're coming out of a
secret entrance, you can't see who's outside. So if you leave, you
expose yourself and you expose the secret entrance. So you're allowed to
come in because you know you're not being followed, but you're not
allowed to leave, assuming presumably until like nightfall or something. So anyway,
so nobody was allowed to leave. Okay. נהפך
סנדלו של אחד מהם, Nehepach sandalo shel echad meihem, one of them
accidentally wore his sandal backwards. Okay. And they look at the footprint.
So they looked at the footprint of a sandal which had been
put on backwards, so it looked like somebody had been walking out,
not going in. So כסבורים הם אחד מהם יצא, kasvurim heim echad
meihem yatza, they looked at the footprint and they thought somebody had
left. וראו אויבים, v'rau oyvim, and they were afraid that now they
were discovered. ועכשיו באים עליהם, v'achshav ba'im aleihem, and now the enemies
are going to come and attack us. דחקו זה בזה, dachaku zeh
bazeh, they all pushed against one another. והרגו זה את זה, v'hargu
zeh es zeh, and they killed one another trying to run out,
you know, in the in the crowds, so hopefully not intentionally. יותר
ממה שהרגו בהם אויבים, Yoser mima shehargu bahem oyvim, more than the
enemies ever killed among them or at least in this
event. רבי אלעאי בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Ilai ben Elazar omer, במערה
היו יושבין. beme'ara hayu yoshvin. No, it's true it was the cave
and it's true that they killed each other on their way trying
to get out of the cave, but it wasn't because the sandal
was backwards. They were in the cave, and כסבורים היו שם... v'kasvurim
hayu sham... במערה היו
יושבין, beme'ara hayu yoshvin, ושמעו קול מעל גבי המערה, v'shamu kol me'al
gabei hame'ara, they heard somebody above the cave. כסבורים
היו שבאו עליהם אויבים, kasvurim hayu sheba'u aleihem oyvim, they thought again
the enemies were coming. דחקו זה בזה והרגו זה את זה יותר
ממה שהרגו בהם אויבים. dachaku zeh bazeh v'hargu zeh es zeh yoser
mima shehargu bahem oyvim. And they killed more than any than the
enemies did. Now in the first version, you understand why the focus
on the shoe because it was the shoe that made them think
that they were somebody had left. What about the second version? So
you could say that maybe the sound that, so if you look
at תוספות, Tosafot, ושמעו קול מעל גבי המערה, v'shamu kol me'al gabei
hame'ara, קול של סנדל המסומר, kol shel sandal hamesumar, that
the sound... Now you could also imagine by the way that because
it was nailed, might have been why they got killed, because maybe
it was like the nails were coming from the bottom of a
כלי *kli*. And that, you know, but it will seem from the
later גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that that's not the case, that actually we're
talking about that the nails were not exposed, they were just nailed
together two halves of a shoe, and that actually nails that are
coming out and protruding in are cleats were not included in this.
So, it does not seem like it was the sandal, it was
the nail part of the sandal that caused that directly, you know,
killed each other, but because the sandal was involved in what led
to the fear, and the fear ultimately led to people being killed.
So that's story number two. Now story number three. רמי בר יחזקאל
אמר *Rami bar Yechezkel amar*, בבית הכנסת היו יושבים *beveis haknesses hayu
yoshvim*, they were in a synagogue, ושמעו קול *v'shamu kol*, and again,
they were hiding from, you know, from the Romans, ושמעו קול מאחורי
בית הכנסת *v'shamu kol me'achorei beveis haknesses*. They heard some sound from
the back of the synagogue, again presumably you'd have to say it
was the sound of these sandals walking. כסבורין היו שבאו עליהם אויבים
*kasvorin hayu shebau aleihem oyvim*, again they thought they were about to
be attacked. דחקו זה את זה והרגו זה את זה יותר ממה
שהרגו בהם האויבים *dachaku zeh es zeh vehargu zeh es zeh yoser
mima shehargu bahem haoyvim*. Okay, same story. ובאותה שעה אמרו *u've'osah sha'ah
amru*, at that moment they said, אל יצא אדם בסנדל המסומר *al
yetzei adam besandal hamesumar*. A person should not wear this nailed sandal.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אי הכי *ei hachi*, if that's
true, בחול נמי ליסר *bechol nami lissar*, Michael says, what does that
have to do with שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*? Let it be forbidden on
the weekday? No, מעשה שהיה בשבת היה *ma'aseh shehayah beShabbos hayah*. The
story happened on שבת Shabbat *Shabbos*. Now, it's not just that as
we'll see in a minute, it's also that, look, it's like, you
know, they asked רב אושעיה *Rav Oshie* if you could listen to
recorded music during the three weeks. So he said, no, it's אסור
assur. *assur*. So they said, well why? It's, you know, it's only
recorded, it's not live? He said, look, I think it's אסור *assur*
the whole year, but they don't listen to me the rest of
the year. So, if you just say you can never wear some
piece of clothing in the rest of the week, that's going to...
it doesn't fit into anything. Why? But on שבת *Shabbos* we already
know there's a million things you can't do and a million different
types of objects of clothing you're not allowed to wear. So we
add this to the list, you'll people will listen to you. Anyway,
we'll see, but that, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, you know,
ties it in that it happened on שבת *Shabbos*. So let's read
a little more, then I'll take some questions. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
said, ביום טוב לישתרי *beyom tov lishari*, let it be permissible on
יום טוב Yom Tov *Yom Tov*? אלמה תנן *almah tnan*,
why do we teach in a משנה *Mishnah* in ביצה *Beitzah*? We'll
read the whole thing although put some of it in parentheses because
some of this isn't in the משנה *Mishnah*. משלחין כלים ביום טוב
בין תפורין בין שאינן תפורין *mishalchin keilim beyom tov bein tforin bein
she'einan tforin*, you can send various items to somebody on יום טוב
*Yom Tov* whether they're sewn up or not sewn up. Basically the
rule is as long as they're an item that in theory could
be used during the rest of the week, you can send them
as a gift on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. אבל לא סנדל המסומר
*aval lo sandal hamesumar*, you cannot send a nailed sandal, ולא מנעל
שאינו תפור *velo min'al she'eino tafur*, and not a, and not a
shoe that is not sewn, because those really have no purpose. So
clearly it's implicit that you have no use for this sandal on
יום טוב *Yom Tov*. You can't wear it on יום טוב *Yom
Tov* either. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, בשבת מאי טעמא *beShabbos
mai ta'ama*, no so listen, why can't you wear on שבת *Shabbos*?
דאיכא כינופיא *de'ika kinufia*, because שבת *Shabbos* people are gathered together. So
you don't want it re-enacts somewhat of the original offense. A lot
of people, crowds, wearing these shoes. Again, it makes you think that
the shoe itself could injure somebody, but we haven't said that yet.
Anyway, crowds and wearing these shoes, that's what we don't like. ביום
טוב נמי איכא כינופיא *beyom tov nami ika kinufia*, similar thing, although
the event happened on שבת *Shabbos* not on יום טוב *Yom Tov*,
but it's similar, a lot of crowds, therefore we don't want people
wearing these shoes. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, one minute, exactly, so
the גמרא *Gemara* says, look, it can't just be crowds. תענית ציבור
איכא כינופיא *ta'anis tzibbur ika kinufia*, how about like תשעה באב *Tisha
B'Av* or תענית ציבור *ta'anis tzibbur*, everybody's getting together. It's a huge
group, you know, people gathered together to דאוון *daven*, big, we get
the whole community together. So why not say it should be forbidden
then? So finally the גמרא *Gemara* admits that part of this has
to do with the fact that you're not allowed to do מלאכה
*melacha*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, no, מעשה שהיה בכינופיא דאיסורא *ma'aseh
shehayah bechinufia de'issura*,
when it happened it was a crowd and it was time when
you were prohibited to do certain things. It was שבת *Shabbos*. הכא
כינופיא דהיתירא *hacha kinufia de'heteira*, on תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av* you're getting
together, true, but there's no, it's not like any acts are forbidden.
I mean, well, eating is forbidden, but not like a type of
מלאכות *melachos* are forbidden. הוה *havah*. So basically what the גמרא *Gemara*
is saying is, and this is I really think the way it's
not just that somewhat it parallels the original circumstances, but as I
said, the fact is that it's if you're saying you can't do
something on שבת *Shabbos*, it fits into a pattern of a lot
of things you can't do on שבת *Shabbos* and there's a list
of clothing you can't wear on שבת *Shabbos*, so therefore it's a
way of giving some, you know, memory to this event, some acknowledgment
of this event in a context in which the actual גזירה gezeirah
*gezeirah* people will listen to and it will be adopted.
So you are or are not allowed to wear it on יום
טוב *Yom Tov*?
You cannot, because יום טוב *Yom Tov* also is a time when
things are forbidden and it's somewhat similar to the experiences of שבת
*Shabbos*.
But you're allowed to carry on יום טוב
*Yom Tov* though, so what's the concern? It's not about carrying, it's
about we don't want you wearing this because of the event that
happened. It's a memorial for that event. It's not a carrying concern.
Why do we only do it on שבת *Shabbos*? Because you'll listen
to us on שבת *Shabbos*. That's the way I'm reading the גמרא
*Gemara*. But anyway, the point being that it's similar to the circumstances
of the event. So the גמרא *Gemara* says, ואפילו לרבי חנניה בן
עקביא Chananya ben Akavya, דאמר לא אסרו אלא בירדן ובספינה כמעשה שהיה
*v'afillu l'Rabbi Chanania ben Akavia d'amar lo asru ela beYarden u'vesfina k'ma'aseh
shehayah*.
So we have another type of case where they forbade something based
on an experience that happened. Although this makes more sense. They were
carrying ashes of a פרה אדומה Parah Adumah. and they were carrying
it over a boat, and then at the end they found a
dead body at the bottom of the boat and they had to
sort of and that's it, end of all the ashes of the
פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah So they said from now on we don't
want anybody transporting ashes of a פרה אדומה on any boat, on
any bodies of water. So they broadened it. But רבי חנינא בן
עקיבא Rabbi Chanina ben Akiva said no, no, no, we're only going
to prohibit the exact same circumstances. Don't do it unless it's not
any type of carrying, it's only on a boat and not any
type of a vessel, only a boat, and not any body of
water, only the Jordan River, which was what the story was וכמעשה
שהיה. u'k'maaseh she'hayah. So normally he wanted to be similar to the
original event if you're going to say this. Now by the way
I should say there it makes more sense because there at least
you could understand that we're concerned that if you convey it by
water there'll be some
opportunity, it'll lead to a situation that'll become טמא. Okay, at least
there you could understand that there's an active concern in applying it
to the next case as well. But even there, even where there's
a more prevalent concern, חנינא בן עקיבא Chanina ben Akiva says only
in the exact same circumstances. Even though he says that here by
the shoe he would agree that we broaden it. Why? הני מילי
ירדן דשאני משאר נהרות. hani mili Yarden d'shani mish'ar neharos. That's by
the Jordan, a Jordan River is different than other rivers. It's longer,
it's deeper, whatever, it's different shape. אבל יום טוב ושבת כי הדדי
נינהו. aval Yom Tov v'Shabbos k'hadadei ninhu. Yom Tov and Shabbos are
more or less the same. דתנן אין בין יום טוב לשבת אלא
אוכל נפש בלבד. d'tnan ein bein Yom Tov l'Shabbos ela ochel nefesh
bilvad. The only difference is whether you can do things for cooking.
I don't know, you're asking me, one river is just like the
next although I have no experience with rivers. I know rivers are
radically different. But anyway, Yom Tov and Shabbos, oh that's a big
difference, you can do cooking on Yom Tov. Anyway so the גמרא
says even חנניה בן עקיבא Chananya ben Akiva would admit that here
we broadened it and we didn't just limit it to שבת. Yes.
Why would they be taking red heifer ashes away from the בית
המקדש? Beis Hamikdash?
I don't know, I'd have to check that case again, but maybe
they were going the opposite direction. Maybe they were transporting it from
one part of
it... you can do the sprinkling anywhere, so maybe they wanted to
make it more convenient for people in other parts of Israel to
become טהור. tahor. Why is that such a crazy idea? Okay, all
right, yes.
Is this the son of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who said that?
Yeah, I don't know, I have to check, I really don't know
because if you look at the side, I almost pronounced it this
way, it's חנניה בן עקביא, Chananya ben Akavya okay, not עקיבא, Akiva,
עקביא, Akavya, and we do have that, because I think חנניה בן
עקביא Akavya we have elsewhere. So I think, right, I think it's
עקביא and not עקיבא. Akiva. Anyway, so now you've got the idea
of that there was this event, there's no real שבת concern, it's
not even like the ashes where you could say the next time
there's a concern it'll be טמא. There's no real שבת concern, but
there was this terrible event that occurred with this sandal and we
want to memorialize it, so we say don't wear it, and we
say don't wear it on שבת or don't wear it on יום
טוב because that's somewhat similar to the original event or as the
גמרא says it's also a time of איסור, issur, so therefore presumably
this edict will be meaningful.
So it's not directly סכנה, sakanah, right? Because then you'd have to
say even on חול chol it should be אסור.
Exactly, exactly, it does not seem like I said that the... that
they're cleats. It seems like it's, we'll see actually cleats are ironically
are okay. So let's keep on reading in the גמרא. אמר רב
יהודה אמר שמואל לא שנו לחזק. Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel lo
shanu l'chazek. That's only a problem when it's just like those original
sandals where the nails are there to strengthen it, to keep it
like, to give it... to keep it together. אבל לנוי, aval l'noy,
sometimes you have studs in something to just look nice, right? So
if the nails are there just for ornament purposes, מותר, mutar, that's
not like the original sandals and that's permissible. וכמה לנוי, v'kamah l'noy,
how many nails would you say would still be considered to be
for ornament and are not so many that they're there clearly to
also keep it together? רבי יוחנן אמר חמש בזה וחמש בזה, Rabbi
Yochanan amar chamesh b'zeh v'chamesh b'zeh, five on each sandal. רבי חנינא
אמר שבע בזה ושבע בזה, Rabbi Chanina amar sheva b'zeh v'sheva b'zeh,
seven on each sandal. אמר ליה רבי יוחנן לשמן בר אבא, Amar
lei Rabbi Yochanan l'Shemen bar Abba, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said to
שמן בר אבא, Shemen bar Abba, אסברא לך לדידי, asbra lach l'didi,
let me explain to you our different positions. לדידי, l'didi, for me,
שתים מכאן ושתים מכאן ואחת בתרסיותיו, shtayim mikan u'shtayim mikan v'achas b'tarsiyosav,
two on the instep, two on the outer part of the shoe
and one on the strap. That would be a nice sort of
maybe symmetry or balance and that's considered ornament. לרבי חנינא, l'Rabbi Chanina,
גימל מכאן וגימל מכאן ואחת בתרסיותיו, gimmel mikan u'gimmel mikan v'achas b'tarsiyosav,
three on the instep, three on the outside
and one on the strap. And that's considered ornament, it's not considered
to be for strength. This is going to be a not very
conceptual גמרא. The rest of the דף daf is going to be
figuring out which shoes does this גזירה gezeirah apply to?
And the whole גזירה gezeira is to only to commemorate this original
event. Okay, so anyway let's take a look. מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll ask
you on this: סנדל הנוטה, sandal hanoteh, if you have an imbalanced
shoe, part of it has of the sole has worn thinner than
the other part and you need to like restore the balance. So
עושה לו שבע, oseh lo sheva, you... make seven nails, and that's
still not a problem for this שבת הלכה, halacha. because then they're
not, it's interestingly that's not, the גמרא's assuming that's in the לנוי
lenoi category, it's not done fundamentally to make the shape of the
shoe, to hold the shoe together, it's done for some other purpose
and it's not a problem.
To look more balanced?
No, to be more balanced. It actually is functional, but since it's
not לחזק lechazek in the way of holding the shoe together, it's
okay. As long as seven. דברי רבי נתן. Divrei Rabbi Noson. That's
what Rabbi Noson says. רבי, רבי מתיר בי"ג. Rebbi, Rebbi matir be-yud
gimmel. And Rebbi says
thirteen are okay. So before we had five and seven, here we
have seven and thirteen. So the גמרא says בשלמא לרבי חנינא, bishlama
le-Rabbi Chanina, according to Rabbi Chanina
who said before seven, הוא דאמר כרבי נתן, hu d’amar k’Rabbi Noson,
he says like Rabbi Noson that up to seven is fine. אלא
רבי יוחנן, Ela Rabbi Yochanan, who says five, דאמר כמאן? d’amar keman?
Who's he going like? He says five, here you have seven and
thirteen. Now later the גמרא will say maybe when it's imbalanced it's
a different definition than when it's totally a fine shoe and just
there for ornament. But anyway, now the גמרא says he said five
and here we have seven and thirteen. Who's he going like? הוא
דאמר כרב נהוראי. Hu d’amar k’Rav Nehorai. He's going like Rav Nehorai.
דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, רב נהוראי אומר: Rav
Nehorai omer: ה' מותר וז' אסור. Heh mutar ve-zayin assur. Five yes,
not seven. So Rabbi Yochanan says five, here we have Rav Nehorai.
So we have a position five, a position seven, a position thirteen.
How many nails till it's still okay? אמר ליה איפא לרבא בר
בר חנה. Amar lei Eifa le-Rabba bar bar Chana. So Eifa says
to Rabba bar bar Chana, אתון תלמידי דרבי יוחנן, Atun talmidei de-Rabbi
Yochanan, you are the students of Rabbi Yochanan, עבידו כרבי יוחנן, avidu
k’Rabbi Yochanan, you should go like Rabbi Yochanan who says five. אנן
נעביד כרבי חנינא, Anan na’avid k’Rabbi Chanina, we'll go like Rabbi Chanina
who says seven. Now, you I it would be interesting to know
their sandals what would be the what would have been the normal
number of nails because all right they're saying five is okay, seven
is okay, thirteen okay, effectively sort of legislating this גזירה gezeira. out
of existence because if most of their sandals were five or seven,
right, so then effectively there'd be very little application of this גזירה.
gezeira So it'd be interesting to know what those realities were. בעי
מיניה רב הונא מרב אסי. Ba’ei minei Rav Huna me-Rav Assi. So
Rav Huna asked from Rav Assi, חמש מאי? Chamesh mai? Is five
okay? אמר ליה אפילו שבע מותר. Amar lei afilu sheva mutar. Seven's
fine, even seven. So then he figured, oh okay, I'm on a
roll, so let's maybe תשע מאי? Tesha mai? How about nine? אמר
ליה אפילו תמניא. Amar lei afilu temanya. No, even eight is no
good, but when I said seven I meant exactly seven. Seven is
okay, any more no good. Anyway. בעי מיניה ההוא רצנא, Ba’ei minei
hahu ratzana, so a certain shoemaker asked מרבי אמי, mi-Rabbi Ammi, from
Rabbi Ammi. טפלו מבפנים מהו? Tephalo mibifnim mahu? So how about if
you if you sewed into the inside of a sandal some type
of a like of an inner sleeve? So now when you put
it on, like it actually you know as opposed to a sandal
where you have the straps over your bare foot, now actually you
have some type of a you know lining and some type of
a of a of a cover around your foot. This is common.
What? It's very common. Oh it is common for sandals? Oh no
for regular shoes. For regular shoes. Right, so that's basically the point
that you made you sort of transformed the sandal this way. So
what's the story? So is it still a sandal? So so he
said אמר ליה מותר, amar lei mutar, it's מותר. mutar. ולא ידענא
מאי טעמא. Velo yadana mai tama. I don't know why. So why
are you saying it's מותר? mutar? So actually he says I mean
I heard from my rebbe it was מותר mutar but I don't
know why. Why shouldn't it be? So that's what that's what the
גמרא's going to say. אמר רב אשי ולא ידע מר מאי טעמא?
Amar Rav Ashi velo yada mar mai tama? What, you can't figure
out the reason why it's okay? כיון דטפלו מבפנים, Keivan de-tephalo mibifnim,
if you sewed this sleeve on in the inside, הוה ליה מנעל.
hava lei minal. You turned it into a shoe. It's no longer
a sandal. בסנדל גזרו בה רבנן במנעל לא גזרו בה רבנן. Besandal
gazru bei rabbanan biminal lo gazru bei rabbanan. It has the same
number of nails but it's no longer a sandal. The גזירה is
by a sandal, not by your shoe. So all these different ways
about cutting away at this category to make it smaller and smaller.
בעי מיניה רבי אבא בר זבדא מרבי אבא בר אבינא. Ba’ei minei
Rabbi Abba bar Zavda mi-Rabbi Abba bar Avina. So Rabbi Abba bar
Zavda asked from Rabbi Abba bar bar Avina, עשאו כמין כלבוס מאי?
Asao k’min kalbos mai? Let's say the nails are not straight nails.
Let's say they're more like hook nails. You have a picture on
the side. There's got to be a name for them. But a
nail that has like two points, you know it's curved, you see
the curve like this, right? Like a staple. Essentially it's like a
staple. Let's say you have a nail that's like a staple, what
would that story be? אמר ליה מותר. Amar lei mutar. That's fine.
So you got the exact same shoe with the exact same number
of nails except rather than straight nails you have more like you
know bended staple nails and now it's okay because it's not the
exact same. And people would have been able to see I mean
it's kind of it must have been kind of obvious? Well yeah
because you would see you would see the metal bar that connects
the two halves, right? If you have a staple on top you
see the line that covers the two. Anyway, מותר. mutar. Okay, so
איתמר נמי הכי, itmar nami hachi, it was also taught, אמר רבי
יוסי ברבי חנינא, amar Rabbi Yosi be-Rabbi Chanina, עשאו כמין כלבוס, asao
k’min kalbos, if you make it like this type of a of
a you know semicircle, of a staple, מותר, mutar, it's permissible. אמר
רב ששת: Amar Rav Sheshes: חיפו כולו במסמרות, Chipo kulo be-masmaros, כדי
שלא תכלה ארעא, kedei shelo tichleh ara, if it's filled with nails
so the ground doesn't eat away with it. Now this means like
it's cleats. You have the staples nails coming out from the bottom
so they're the thing you know grabbing into the ground rather than
the sole of the shoe, מותר, mutar, that's permissible. Now that is
the most dangerous of all. I mean something with metal cleats. You
know, but no, that wasn't the case that originally was. It's also
interesting because, you know, why is that מותר *mutar* to wear on
שבת *Shabbos*? Aren't you like digging up the ground? So that raises
interesting questions about פסיק רישא *psik reisha*, ולא ניחא ליה *velo nicha
lei* or whatever. Maybe I don't know, maybe the bottoms were more
flat, then maybe they weren't pointed. But anyway, it's not there just
to hold it together, it's there to serve as some type of
a cleat, that's okay. תניא כוותיה דרב ששת *Tanya kavatei d'Rav Sheshet*.
I know. We taught like רב ששת *Rav Sheshet*, לא יצא האיש
בסנדל המסומר *lo yeitzei ha'ish besandal hamusumar*. You should not go out
with this nailed sandal. ולא יטייל מבית לבית *velo yetayel mibeis leveis*
אפילו ממיטה למיטה *afillu mimittah lemittah*. Now, just to show you, because
it's not about carrying, we don't let you even walk from one
house to the next with them, and even from one bed, like
one room to another room in your own house, you're not supposed
to wear it at all, even indoors. So it's really, you know,
because it's like
supposed to be completely off-limits, it's really just not about
carrying or anything, it's just about this issue about commemoration.
אבל מטלטלין אותו לכסות בו את הכלי *aval metaltelin oso lechasos bo
es hakeli* ולסמוך בו כרעי המיטה *velismoch bo karei hamittah*. You can
use it to, you know, in a non-wearing capacity. You can use
it to support a bed, to cover a vessel. Meaning, the way
תוספות *Tosafos* brings it, it's like a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור kli she-melachto
l'isur. *kli shemlachto l'issur*. It's something that we don't let you wear
on שבת *Shabbos*, so its primary function is לאיסור *l'issur*, like a
hammer. You can't use it for its primary function on שבת *Shabbos*.
What's the הלכה *halacha* of a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור *kli shemlachto l'issur*?
You can use it for a permissible function. So the forbidden function
is wearing it, the permissible function is doing something else with it,
supporting a bed, covering a vessel. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אוסר *Rabbi
Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon oser*. רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון *Rabbi Elazar b'Rabbi Shimon*
says, I don't want you touching this at all on שבת *Shabbos*,
even for some other purpose. So you see there was this real
thing of making a taboo around this type of a thing, but
not, you know, all because of presumably to commemorate this event. But
why did they say the thing happened because of the shoe? No,
yeah, but not because of the spikes. I mean, we would have
thought it was the spikes. But what's the point to do this?
Some bad event happened and someone happens to be wearing this shoe,
which was somehow connected to the event. It doesn't make sense. Yeah,
I mean, it's a good question whether, you know, whether the גמרא
*Gemara* thinks that there's—look, the way I've been reading this is that
the גמרא *Gemara* is trying to limit and limit and limit this,
like legislate it almost out of existence, because it could be that
in the immediate aftermath of the event, you could understand why people
would sort of try to do something. Oh my god, it was
such a tragedy, nobody should be ever wearing this thing again, or
whatever. You know, and that—okay, that's in the immediate aftermath. A hundred
years later, what's the point? To remember that there was once this
tragedy? And, you know, but what does it have to do with
the shoe? And whatever. So I think that could be why it's
being the sort of shrunk, the application of this, because maybe it
did not have any continuing resonance. It was a practice that was
adopted in the immediate aftermath, which shouldn't have so much continuing resonance.
And maybe I think that's why it's trying to be—they're trying to
narrow the scope of it.
That's the way I read this. Why wouldn't they say forget about
it? Oh, come on, that's—that's not the way הלכה *halacha* works. Okay.
So, what way? Every now and then you directly confront something and
you undo it, but that's, you know, that raises against challenges. It
says, you know, a תקנה *takkanah* you're not supposed to reverse unless
you have an equal base or whatever. So the more normal way
it works is by redefining the categories in such a way that
it's almost not applicable, which is I think what we see is
happening here. Yes, those cleats would be very practical on שבת *Shabbos*
if you started plowing. Right, well, we mentioned that, that that could
be a problem with cleats if it's a פסיק רישא *psik reisha*,
אם ניחא ליה *im nicha lei*, לא ניחא ליה *lo nicha lei*.
Right, but the גמרא *Gemara* is not asking that issue. Okay, so
let's continue now. It says like this: נשרו רוב מסמרותיו *nashru rov
masmerosev*, if most of the needles have—not needles, nails—have fallen off, ונשתייר
בו ארבע או חמש *venishtayer bo arba o chamesh*, if four or
five are still left, מותר *mutar*, then it's allowed. So here you
see that four or five is okay. רבי מאיר אומר שבע *Rabbi
Meir omer sheva*. רבי *Rabbi* says seven is okay. Now before רבי
*Rabbi* said five, so we'll have to deal with that. חיפהו בעור
מלמטה וקבע לו מסמרותיו מלמעלה מותר *chifahu be'or milmata vekava lo masmerosev
milmala mutar*. Let's say what you did is that you had it
covered with like leather, you put some type of leather insole, I
think if I understand רש״י *Rashi* correctly, insole inside the sandal, and
then you had nails to hold the leather insole in, then that's
okay as long as it's not the nails that are holding like
the two parts of the actual—hard... what is a sandal made out
of? Is it made out of wood or what? Leather. It is
leather, right? For non-Jews it's made out of all kinds of fabric
and
everything, but by Jews it's leather.
So I don't know what it means that you've covered it with
leather if the whole thing is leather. But anyway, it's not the
primary hard leather that is the base. So then if the nails
are holding that in, that's okay. But the problem is when the
nails are combining like the two halves of the base. Okay, עשהו
כמין קולבוס *asahu kemin kulbus*, if you made it like this hook,
like this staple, או כמין טס *o kemin tas*, or רש״י *Rashi*
says if let's say the nails are very like flat, you know,
so it's not— standard sort of long and thin and pointy nail,
it's more like a plate. או כמין יתד or it's or it's
like a peg, right, it's not like it doesn't have the exact
shape of a nail. או שחיפיהו כולו במסמרות o she-chipeyhu kulo b'masmerot
or if he covered it entirely with nails כדי שלא תאכלהו קרקע
kedei she-lo tokhelehu karka so that it's not eaten away by the
ground. מותרת ופוסלה. mutteret u-posla. So again all these exceptions. So the
Gemara says: wait, we've got a problem. הגופא קשיא. ha gufa kashya.
אמרת נשרו רוב מסמרותיה ואף על פי שנשתיירו בה שבע. amarta nashru
rov masmeroteiha v'af al pi she-nishtayru bah sheva. First you said if
most of the nails fell out it's okay, meaning even if there's
a lot of nails left as long as most fell out it's
okay. והדר תני ארבע וחמש. v'hadar tani arba v'chamesh. And then you
said only four or five is okay, more than that, טפי לא,
tfei lo, more no. אמר רב ששת לא קשיא. amar Rav Sheshet
lo kashya. כאן שנגממו כאן שנעקרו. kan she-nigmemu kan she-ne'ekru. It's the
difference whether the nails are worn down or they're completely taken out.
Rashi says if they're worn down you see that they were there,
so then people understand that even though there's a lot of nails
now, they understand that it's a remnant of what used to be
and as long as there's only a minority you're okay. But if
some of the nails have been completely pulled out, people will think
לכתחילה lechatchila it was made this way and therefore more than four
and five is no good. All right. ארבע וחמש מותר. arba v'chamesh
mutar. Four and five is okay. השתא חמש שרי ארבע מיבעיא. hashta
chamesh sharei arba mibaya. If you said five is good, why do
you have to say four is good? אמר רב חסדא ארבע מסנדל
קטן וחמש מסנדל גדול. amar Rav Chisda arba mi-sandal katan v'chamesh mi-sandal
gadol. Fine, four on a small sandal, five on a big sandal.
רבי מתיר עד שבע. Rebbi matir ad sheva. Rebbi says seven. והתניא
רבי מתיר עד שלוש עשרה. v'hatanya Rebbi matir ad shelosh esrei. Didn't
we say before that Rebbi says thirteen? I may have said it
wrong before anyway. Didn't we say before Rebbi said thirteen? לא קשיא.
lo kashya. No, it's different. נוטה שאני. noteh shani. No, when did
he say thirteen? That's when it was imbalanced, so then you're allowed
more nails to rebalance it. Here where it's just there for ornament
and therefore only until seven. So the Gemara says: השתא דאתית להכי.
hashta d'atit lehachi. Now that we're saying the numbers we gave before,
remember before we said seven and thirteen, that those are specifically in
the case of imbalanced sandal, we allow more nails. So now that
you said this, רבי יוחנן נמי. Rabbi Yochanan nami. When Rabbi Yochanan
said five, when we thought how could he say five if we
have opinions of seven and thirteen? לא קשיא. lo kashya. That's also
not difficult. נוטה שאני. noteh shani. Seven and thirteen is when it's
imbalanced, then we allow more nails. When we're saying other numbers like
five or seven, that's when it's totally balanced and they and we're
allowing a certain amount of nails just because we're saying it's fundamentally
ornament, it's not לחזק. lechazek. Okay. אמר רב מסנא ואמרי לה אמר
רב אחדבוי בר מתנה אמר רב מסנא. amar Rav Masna v'amri lah
amar Rav Achdaboi bar Matna amar Rav Masna. אין הלכה כרבי אלעזר
ברבי שמעון. ein halacha k'Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon. We don't look Rabbi
Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon that says it's completely off limits, you can't wear
it but we do say you're allowed to use it for other
things. So the Gemara says: פשיטא. pshita. It's obvious. יחיד ורבים הלכה
כרבים. yachid v'rabim halacha k'rabim. He's an individual and he's arguing against
a majority, we go like the majority. No. מהו דתימא מסתברא טעמיה
דרבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון בהא. mahu d'teima mistabra tamei d'Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi
Shimon be-ha. Maybe Rabbi Elazar b'Rebbi Shimon's position makes sense. Why? So
Rashi says maybe it makes sense because if we let you move
it you'll come to wear it. But Tosfos says maybe it makes
sense because maybe since fundamentally this is about like commemorating this event,
maybe we want to make it complete taboo on Shabbat and make
it worse than a hammer. A hammer you can use to crack
nuts, this is worse than a כלי שמלאכתו לאיסור. We want to
make it completely off limits, so maybe we would have said that.
קמשמע לן. ka mashma lan. That no, that we're not treating it
any worse than a hammer. Something you can't wear but it's something
you can use in another circumstance. אמר רבי חייא. amar Rabbi Chiya.
אי לאו דקרו לי בבלאי שרי. ei lav d'karu li Bavla'ei sharei.
This is great. If it not been if I would not be
afraid that people would call me the permitting Babylonian, okay, ah, you're
the meikil Babylonian, we know all about you because Rabbi Chiya came
from Bavel to Eretz Yisrael. שרינא בה טובא. sharena bah tuva. I
would have allowed a much wider range of cases. So you see
that there is this you know there's this impetus, there's this trying
to make it more and more permissible. And he says you know
ha I would have made it much even even more interesting from
Bavel because maybe in Eretz Yisrael where the event happened it still
had some of that resonance, right, maybe in Bavel it had very
little resonance. Anyway he's saying if they don't I don't want them
to call me the lenient Babylonian but if I wasn't afraid of
that I would מתיר matir a much wider range of cases. What
are they? So כמה? kama? How much would you have allowed? בפומבדיתא
אמרין עשרין וארבע. be-Pumbedita amrin esrin v'arba. Up to twenty-four up to
up to twenty-four nails would have been okay. בסורא אמרין עשרין ותרין.
be-Sura amrin esrin v'tarein. Twenty-two nails. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק וסימנך.
amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak v'simanach. The way to remember it is
עד דאתי מפומבדיתא לסורא חסר תרתי. ad d'ati mi-Pumbedita l'Sura chasar tartei.
From the time it takes you to walk from Pumbedita to Sura
two of your nails will fall out. So one is twenty-four and
one is twenty-two. So anyway what you see from the upshot of
this Gemara like I said not a very conceptual Gemara. a lot
about how many nails in the shoe, but what you do see
is a constant shrinking of it. X number of nails it's still
okay, if it's filled with nails it's okay, and if you've got
this thing sitting nailed into it and if you've got a sleeve
it's okay and all these different ways of narrowing the scope. And
I think it's exactly as I said that you know that the
it really lost its resonance and therefore it was sort of being
legislated more and more out of existence and maybe also interesting the
difference between בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael exactly around how
much were they still sort of feeling some of the resonance of
this גזרה. gezeirah. Yes, Charlie. Any הלכה למעשה Halacha L'maiseh applications of
this? Not that I know of, unless you've got a sandal with
a lot of nails. But a lot of a lot of men's
shoes at least have nails in them. I guess a lot of
those tiny little nails. But it's but it would only be a
sandal. I don't think sandals tend to have nails, right? Some do.
All right, it would be interesting to see if anybody continues to
to attach a second leather layer on the heel. A lot of
them, like this? Yeah. I mean really? The heel was okay, but
it was just like the top. All right, I'll have to see
if anybody really applies it. And we'll let רבקה Rivka we'll let
רבקה Rivka. have the last word here. רבקה. In any case, it's
more than just a bit of splitting of hairs, right? About how
many nails on a shoe? But the bottom line is that it
really doesn't matter. There's no truth, there's no objective Halachic fact. It's
just the Rabbi's reputation. That's what he's saying if I want to
be a friend. Oh, so the last point! The Rabbi here is
one of the most important of the late תנאים Tannaim and he
is afraid to פסקן. pasken. Of all these Rabbis weighing in over
how much decoration or nails on the foot. Well, it is true,
it is not an issue, it's not about issues or conceptual. But
again, what I see is very nice and this is a part
of the Halachic process is that there are different ways in which,
you know, through legislation, even if you don't directly, you know, and
you're not able to for various reasons, either on the books you're
not directly able to contradict a ruling or because sometimes because of
social pressure. Okay, but you know what? It might have not mattered
because if people would reject it, it wouldn't have done any good
anyway. But this, I think, it reflects a certain reality that sometimes
there's certain ways you can operate within a system and certain ways
you can't. And they still managed to very significantly limit. I'll just
end by telling you a story. You know, the question that bothers
everybody by שבת is that you can't take medicine on שבת unless
you're seriously sick because we're afraid you'll grind medicine. And we say,
oh, you know, though, who grinds medicine nowadays? Why does it have
to be an issue? But the law's on the books. One or
two presuppositions say you can completely, it completely doesn't apply, but people,
you know, aren't willing to hear that because, you know, you're not
able to just cross something out. So they say that רב סולובייצ'יק
Rav Soloveitchik used to say, look, he says, if, if you're really
sick, then you can take it anyway. It's so you can take
medicine. And if you're not really sick, then it's not medicine, so
you can take it. So, so the point is, there's ways you
keep the law on the books, but when they stop being so
relevant, especially these types of rabbinic, you know, there are different ways
through the reinterpretation that these things can evolve. That's part of the
Halachic system. So I think that is certainly what you see from
today's דף. daf. All right.